I was thinking about the Buddha's uh
practice before he
was enlightened because that kind of
enlightened because that kind of
indicates what you need to be doing you
know and he says that in a few sutas
what he was doing before not just
aesthetic practices but things that
actually leading up to that leading up
to his attempts yeah towards Nana things
are really help
and uh one of those was that two kinds of
uh one of those was that two kinds of
thoughts Sut where where he divided his
thoughts into two
classes the unbeneficial and the
beneficial and so when he saw the
unbeneficial when an unbeneficial
thought arose he saw that it wasn't for
his own good or the good of others it
didn't lead to Freedom
pieace and in just that kind of seeing
the danger of those types of thoughts
that is when they subsided and
ended just by contemplating the danger
thinking about it yes yeah right so but
the thing
is
um that's the root of the problem the
root of the problem
is a thought a dhama a mental image
affected with craving affected with
desire affected with ill will um
affected with hindrances put it that
way so in order to in order to be able
to see the problem on that
level to recognize that the problem is
indeed on the level of a mental image uh
you need to start practicing withdrawal
from everything all the
behaviors that depend that
exist on the basis of corrupted mental
image so that's why again in in like in
all the sutas and whenever the Buddha
was describing the whole idea of that
gradual training is it has to start with virtue
training is it has to start with virtue
has to start with uncompromising
principles around the whole some
Behavior choices responsibility
recognizing your intentions as
the kind of one of the decisive factors
whether things will be wholesome or UNH
wholesome so virtue sense restraint all
that purification is just to bring you
closer and closer to actually recognize
that source for yourself like everybody
can wrap their head around idea that oh
yeah the thought is the root of the
problem but you don't really that that
that information does not sink in does
not become knowledge or understanding
because you can you can try and address
your thoughts all you want you can
manage them you can counter them but if
your behavior is not dried up from all
the UN wholesome choices you're making
on account of already corrupted images
it will make no difference it's as I
said before it's like trying to like
cleaning your
skin while def festering infection
remains untreated so it's like you could
make it look clean but it's fact as
infected in dirty environment completely
dirty exactly so and the whole
purification of the gold simil in the
sutas you don't start by picking up the
the the the microscopic impurities with
with tweezers and stuff like while there
is still uh coarse filth floating in the
same liquid so you need to start by by by
liquid so you need to start by by by
removing that but of course the whole
purpose of uh sense restraint training
self-training in terms of virtue and
responsibility we often talk about is to
reveal to you that yeah your mental
images are the root of the problem have
you grasped signs and features of the
grasped signs and features of the
beautiful out of the Habit out of the
dependence on desire out of seeking the
pleasures or have you not grasped signs
and features of what what your mind is
trying to present you
with and if you if you do reach that
level you recognize oh at this point
here all I need to do is recognize
whether an Arisen mental
image is partaking in any of the
hindrance or not and if it isn't I'm
blameless and I'm burden and I have no I
don't need to do anything about
it I don't even need to keep the
precepts I don't even need to be
restrained cuz you will be cuz the
reasons for breaking the precepts the
reason for the lack of the restraint is
you already have taken up or
allowed these mental images of the
corrupt nature rooted in greed aversion
distraction doubt hindrances you are
allowed them to be on that internal
Center Stage that kind of determines
pushes your intentions pushes your
choices and all that and all of that is
not not something you did in the past oh
you know yesterday I allowed those
images and that's why today this is
happening yesterday you might have
allowed the wrong images you grasp the
signs and features carelessly you allow
them to proliferate you you you fuel
them to to proliferate more but if
that's still happening today is because
today there is still connection to the
same images on the same level you are
still doing it in other
words so how do you then stop and then
people would try to stop you know they
read the sutas like that and then they
think okay I must get rid of these
images I must get rid of the mind that
thinks sensual thoughts but that's
impossible cuz that's see in order for
you to get rid of the pressure that
Central mind exerts on
me I need to be basically be uh I need
to accept those images first in order to
treat them but accepting those corrupt
images it's already giving in
them that's why we always say first and
foremost you don't act up out of those
images doesn't matter the pressure you
know what you will not
do because the images is not a problem
it's just you
willingly picking up the implications of
those images the signs and features the
nitas as the sutas often say and as we
said having seen sight with the eye
heard sound with the ear goes for all
the senses a skilled monk does not pick
signs and features in other words it
does not allow does not focus on signs
and features implicit of Desire implicit
of ill will implicit of distraction of
the hindrances so the signs and features of
hindrances so the signs and features of
the IM the images U whose signs and
features you're not picking up they
remain that's the point that's the bait
if you want to get rid of the bait
you're going to be reaching out and
falling for
bait so the mind of centrality for
example and Central thoughts that want
to come up as I said you want to unfocus
from them not by focusing on something
them not by focusing on something
else which might help as I said in the
beginning it might help if you just try
and think about something else but you
have to be careful whether that whole
project of or I'll think about the
opposite is rooted in trying to get rid
of the entire mind of centrality cuz you
don't want to S you don't want to
experience the discomfort uh of the
pressure that it exts over you or is it
r no no no I'm not trying to get rid of
the mind of
sensuality to kill it to strangle it I'm
trying to teach it that that which it
wants is actually
undesirable but it doesn't know that
that animal doesn't know that sensuality
is actually like burning coals you need
to convey that to it but you can't go to
it if your immediate like a knee-jerk
reaction is pressure of sensuality get
of it get rid of it get rid of it think
the opposite get rid of it that's not a
middle way that's now going completely
the other
way so there pressure sensuality the
Buddha says he doesn't the Buddha
doesn't say oh he gets rid of that mind
no he says he doesn't grasp the signs
and features that are trying to enter
the center stage as we said before it's
like you already know at the back of
your mind peripherally speaking if the
mind is affected with hindrance with
doubt if there is like a lingering ill
will or something
and it wants to it pushes you to
crystallize images and thoughts that
that come from it that's what you don't
do I will not allow the crystallization
of these vague
pressures because I already know what
will crystallize itself in what way it
will be those thoughts would crystallize
themselves in the directions that it
wants to go yeah the Mind wants to go in
those directions it's to send you in
that way but you are the one that gives
that final input of grasping the signs
and features by grasping them in other words
features by grasping them in other words
means allowing them to basically
crystallize and take the center stage
and then you want to deal with them but
you already fell for it that's my
point so when the Buddha divided the
thoughts the mental images into two
classes that's already
included dividing the two the the the
all of the thoughts into two groups
implies already see this ambiguous
pressuring images that are not quite as
crystallized well that's already
recognized as an UNH wholesome thought
because you already know where it would
crystallize you toward words to put it
that way but people usually don't see that as
way but people usually don't see that as
a thought they take it for granted they
take this pressure of something of
sensuality real will and then thoughts
fully crystallized of central thoughts
and and then try to counter them in
order to get rid of the whole
thing you know that suit that we often
mention in
aut how does one free himself from
hindrances it wasn't about changing the
mind or replacing it or or getting rid
of it he was about learning how to
attend through what the mind is trying
to present you with so the mind is
pushing these thoughts to
Forefront your responsibility is to not
allow them to take the center stage and
proliferate them further but instead see
through what's being pushed at you see
what where it comes from so to speak and
it comes from from the mind already
affected by desire already affected by
ill will so when the mind is pressuring
you with negative states to put it that
way you already know what thoughts would
develop if you start proliferating them
and allowing signs and features to take
the center stage so instead by not doing
that but at the same time not trying to
get rid of that mind out of aversion you
are actually dealing with it you are
leaving your own mind that wild animal
you're leaving you're making it stay
with its own pressure with its own
thoughts you don't fall victim of it you
don't act out of it you don't mask and
and blur the waters by getting involved
with it and then it sort of sinks in for
the Mind itself that these thoughts are
unpleasant cu the only reason mind
engages with sensuality mind pressures
you towards acts of sensuality is
because he wants to get rid of those
unpleasant thoughts of
sensuality same with Will same with any
hindrance but it involves you which
basically in return actually just
perpetuates that dependence of your own
mind on on on you acting out on you
blurring the lines so that so that they
can ignore the real problem which is
whether you engage with sensuality or
not whether you engage with ill will or
not presence of those pressures and
signs and features of lust aversion
distraction hindrances it's already
unpleasant in and of itself which is
exactly why the Mind wants you to do
something about
it and if you give into that you're
baited you hooked and you doing
something about it I managing is just
inadvertently fueling it you might on a
on a word in a worldly sense you might
sure like develop a better skill in
management of it so you might not be as
as um as careless as proliferated as
sort of unh wholesome as before but
fundamentally you are still accepting it
accepting that role accepting that
involvement accepting that Sara of that
activity and fundamentally that's all
Mar wants you know like you have people that
wants you know like you have people that
just carelessly go to sensuality then
you have people they say no to that but
they they don't discern the middle way
so that and they try just try to deny
the whole picture either way Mara still
has them as the suit is described and then
them as the suit is described and then
means like okay so sure you can be
engaging carelessly or try and shun the
bait and dismiss the whole thing either
way underneath it all the problem
remains and you are involved and you're
fueling it inadvertently through your
involvement when you you see those
hindrances those directions of the where
the Mind wants to go into and you don't
go in there you you can see them as a
risen yeah inclinations and and that's
point you already know those directions
yeah like when the mind is pressured you
don't need to allow images to
crystallize to know where it wants to
take you you already know so the point
is to train yourself to keep recognizing
that you already
know where the mind is inclining and
that inclination is real as such it's
already a mental image
see in the beginning you think mental
images are only things that you can see
hear smell taste touch then you start
practicing sensory strain then the the
the the threshold for what defines a
mental image increases you recognize
okay even the thoughts and vague sense
um emotions and stuff they're all real
as such they're mental images but see
now even these directions of your
disrupted mind is a mental image is real
as such on that level that is activated
something it's it's activated and it is
an image that you would have already
taken up the signs and features from of
but you won't be able to just stop the
signs and features of these subtle
directions pressures ambiguities unless
you would have practiced the same non-
taking of signs and features of whatever
the mind tries to serve you
with so that's the practice you know we
how many times we say Endurance on the
right level the the cany that the
patients in regard to the bait that the
mind is putting in front of like take it
take it take it it will help both of
us obviously in order to be able to stay
on that right level of not taking the
the the not allowing the center stage
for the images that come out of that
already wrongly inclined mind can only
be developed if you would have withdrawn
yourself from the coarser forms of the
same principle which is Mis misbehavior
by by Body unbeneficial Behavior by Body
by speech
yeah like you need to work that way up
so to
speak and then once those uh UNH
wholesome inclinations have settled
down the Mind actually got the point
means the mind is getting the point yeah
and starts to relax so then even those
pressuring directions that you they
would would have been quite confining in
the beginning you know first time you
start saying no to your desires you just
just feels like you're fully trapped
like inside out is just all of it feels
like it's against you just because
you're so used to in escaping it through
movement of activation of acting by Body
acting by speech acting by
mind that's why generally like when
people hear about sense restraint
celibacy withdrawing from sensuality
it's like the sutas when says oh Master
GOA that sounds like an abyss to a
householder in other words as much as
you would be shocked and frightened
by discovering a massive bottomless
Abyss right in front of your next step
that's how shock and frightened people
are when they hear they have to give up
the sense
desires and then he was praising the
Buddha teaching how those who follow the
Dharma seem to overcome that and then
overcome the
desires because they're not afraid of it
anymore so in that suit that I mentioned
that once the those un wholesome
inclinations the mind's un wholesome
inclinations have settled down subsided
due to his understanding of
them then he lives still diligently but
then a wholesome thought arises and he
knows that yeah and he knows that if he
thinks about this it goes in that
direction there's nothing that can go
wrong it won't lead him yeah later on
even that becomes
unnecessary see when you would have
cultivated the whole when you recognize
the direction is not UNH wholesome you
don't have to act out of that assumed
sense of Duty but I still must deal with
this no you only need to deal with
thoughts that are rooted in hindrances
yeah so that's the so once you start
recognizing that they're not but it's
not something you decide oh now I will
start uh uh changing this practice as
well I will start I will begin now
calming even my wholesome thoughts that
becomes apparent when the time for that
comes but there is no more UNH wholesome
directions coming up from your mind when
every thought that comes up the sentence
stage of an UNH wholesome pressure is
simply doesn't even exist there's a
possibility to engage with then you
realize okay now I could relax I don't
even have to keep an eye on this because
even my own mind now that animal prefers
The Beneficial thoughts over the UN
beneficial how it used to be it's it's
literally the simile of the uh in the
sutas of those cows when they used to
stray and wander into the other people's
crops so constantly you had to no I'm
not allowing them to feed there but
after a while they learn the animals
learned to not go
there and then you recognize that and
then it's like okay now I don't need to
constantly I can even lay down and sleep
and relax when I wake up they're still
where they should be because they don't
want to go into other people's crops but
that's not up to you to decide when that
will happen up to you is to not allow
the sent stage not grasp the signs and
features of the of the pressuring
thoughts not leak towards the
unbeneficial directions on account of
your physical or verbal Behavior yeah
and then the mind when it stops kicking
and screaming in face of the seeming
confinement of restraint will come down
and prefer
it and once it prefers it you realize
now I can trust it I can trust it more
maybe still not fully if you are unsure
but he has shown me that he does prefer
a renunciation because it's factually
better it has shown me that it does
prefer friendliness and non-ill will
because it is factually
better so it's you're seeing the the
danger in those UNH wholesome thoughts
and you're staying clear of that the
inclinations and but that
whole contemplation of that inclination
is UN wholesome that inclination is
going to lead to uh trouble from yeah
yeah that already is that is that this
direction this type of thinking this
inclination to think and to catch any
UNH wholesome inclination is a good
inclination yes you know what I mean and
you can you can actively think about it
as well that's why I said to people like
um when they they they feel like they
need to practice meditation it's like
yes but you need to understand what
meditation is like if you just keep
practicing calming because your mind gets Disturbed
calming because your mind gets Disturbed
as in artificial calming through methods
and techniques that's not uprooting the
problem that's just sort of numbing it
down you really want to practice
meditation in a sense of finding a place
where you're not Disturbed in the first
place so in other words instead of just
trying to blindly calm your mind because
it because it bothers you you need to
recognize why is it Disturbed in the
first place MH why does the Mind want to
disturb things and above all why do I
still give into that and no out of
calming will magically resolve that for
you only frequently thinking it
recollecting your virtue or lack of
thereof um and then making an effort to
improve that so sit for meditation sit
in your meditation and then think why
does your mind get Disturbed and really
clarify that because the Su tells you
because it it engages with unbeneficial
thoughts goes in that direction doesn't
matter if you're mon or man the
unbeneficial thoughts of thoughts
through in great div version delusion in
five hindrances that's the sole reason
for disturbance for everything else so
if you still cultivate them doesn't
matter what you do on top of
it so if you if you do start to
recognize that you can actively then
think about the danger the the the
unbeneficial of these thoughts like
remind yourself just so that your mind
gets to hear it more and more gets to
see get gets to be reminded of those
very perceptions that deep down even
that wild animal can relate to and get
to see that the safety that it's now
abiding it yeah that's that's what you
that's what's going to become apparent
afterwards yeah the safety is not going
to immediately because it's just
everything seems confining and seems
like going against the grain because it
is but if you do that long enough then
you do recognize what's right in front
of you when this has been abandoned the
unbeneficial thoughts allowing the
center stage for for for signs and
features of the unsuitable
kind uh you abandon that you're not
allowing it does doesn't matter the
pressure you remain basically
recognizing where that threshold of your
careless input is uh then one day you
just recognize what's there when that
picture is maintained and what's there
is oh an undisturbed mind loads of the
space of of a trained
animal trust as well that oh I I can
relax CU I do see that if this is the
environment maintained animal cannot go
into other people's pastures I the one
who used to inadvertently open the gate
and let them because they were just
pressuring me too much and I I didn't
mentally I wasn't capable of like uh uh
dealing with it in a sense of you know
somebody pressures you to to to go take
this take or give it to me and harasses
you for it but you realize well doesn't
matter the amount of pressure they put
on me I'm the one who chooses to act
because I don't want to be living with
that pressure and it's like well that's
that's you give into debate but noticing
that's what's then then that safe place
well then then then then your efforts
become verified so to speak all your
effort to withdraw while enduring on the
right level not grasping signs and
features not proliferating not acting
out gets confirmed that it works because
you recognize oh this is a factual
safety yeah that I arrived not through
doing this or that technique or practice
and then just magically got revealed but
simply through withdrawing from
everything that was obstructing
it and knowing clearly that is an
obstruction yeah that is an obstruction
and with joints and well then you will
know even more clearly then you will
start noticing even subtler OB
obstructions that you might not have
noticed before because now you have
actually a palpable reference as to oh
this is the factual safety so right away
you'll see anything that contradicts
that safety or threatens it and anything
that doesn't so then that gives even
more confidence in practice and the path
and the recognition that's that's that's
joh that's then you realize yes you know
there's the peace The Joy the pleasure
of yeah I don't want to use those terms
because people have all these
preconceived notions already so when you
say Jan ah Janna whatever my idea of
Janna is but yeah factually that is
Janna yeah but you can see what Janna
means there yeah complete jna means what
the Su says it means means Thor complete
withdrawal from from the five hindrances
and everything that's unb beneficial
yeah but understanding it all it's
complete understanding Clarity that
arises on account of it yeah I'm
completely safe and then I can actually
now the safety that arrived not through
me fabricating it through one pleasure
or the other is arrived through
withdrawing from any and all dependence
on pleasure of the
senses through withdrawing the Mind from
it recognizing the the the the profound
inherent um unb beneficialness of
it and then finding safety in withdrawal
from that and then sinking in that sinks
into your mind as well that knowledge so
now it's effortless for you because the
mind prefers it as well